You may be seated.
Well, good morning again.
Last week, we launched a new series called What Does the Bible Say About?
We received lots of questions from you all over 20.
We will not have time to answer all of them.
I told you last week that I was very encouraged that you guys did not try and back me into a hot-button cultural topic corner for the most part.
You asked well-thought-out, nuanced theological questions.
Some of you are new believers wrestling with the basic truths of Christianity.
Those are all great questions.
I did receive one difficult, challenging, maybe a bit of a hot-button cultural topic.
And rather than covering it myself, I decided to assign it to somebody else so that if they say something you don't like, I can just pretend like I disagree with it and we can move on.
Yeah, sounds great, right?
So, I want to, in just a moment, welcome to the stage someone who has become a good friend of mine.
His name is Dr. Reverend, I think you do that backwards, Reverend Dr. Stephen Cole.
He is the director, the kind of CEO of our denomination, our family of churches, and sometimes I like to call him the Pope.
He does not like that very much.
And what's cool about our family of churches is that it's really non-hierarchical.
Non?
That's a really hard word to say.
You know what I mean?
Non-hierarchical.
And we function as a family, and so more than a CEO, Stephen really functions like a pastor to all of our pastors.
And so, he has become a friend of mine.
I remember the first time I saw his name come across my caller ID out of the blue, and I answered and said, oh, no, what did I do and how bad is it?
And he said, even if you were in trouble, I really couldn't do much about it.
So, that was very comforting and encouraging to me.
So, I'd love for Canvas, for all of you, to give a very warm welcome to my good friend, Stephen Cole.
I have called him multiple times, and he was in trouble every time.
Can you hear me?
Did you turn it off?
I didn't turn it off, but I told him I was.
And then I just told him that I would, and there it is.
So, there you go.
Joel and I are friends.
We'll get to that in a minute.
So, it is funny to call me the Pope, because I have the least amount of papal authority ever in the history of authority when it comes to ecclesial things, church things.
But we are a relational people.
I like to tell people, on the hierarchy of the Brethren Church, you're a part of that.
If you do not know that, it's a denomination.
We'll get into that in just a second.
There is a small speed bump in the middle, where sometimes, not all the time, I get to stand.
It's a very small, very flat structure.
So, can I come in here and remove anyone?
No.
Can I come in here and do anything about anything you said that's crazy?
Except for, I get to come be your friend and your brother in Christ, and maybe influence you to a different way of thinking, if that was something that was needed.
So, that is the authority that I carry.
I tend to tell people, my authority rises and falls with my staff.
They're the only ones I can fire.
That's it.
Everybody else is fine.
So, even if I called you, you'll be fine.
You'll be fine.
So, my name is Stephen Cole.
I am the executive director.
That's the official title.
It isn't Pope.
And I've been here a few times.
If you've been here when I have preached before, raise your hand.
I didn't think that was.
I thought that was going to happen.
About five of you.
Great.
So, my role is to be a support, to come alongside, to be a brother in Christ, a minister in the gospel with you, alongside you, with a staff of people that do the same and come together to do the work of the kingdom.
That is my job.
And so, I get to do that around the United States.
I get to travel in a lot of places.
And we have mission points in 11 countries, if you count America, 11 countries around the world.
And so, I get to be a part of that as well and travel and be a part of what it means to do ministry together as a body of Christ.
The body of Christ.
Not a local, not just a regional, but the global body of Christ.
So, I get to do that on your behalf and bring greetings to you on behalf of other churches and take your story with me when I go tell your story to other people who need encouragement about what the Lord is doing.
So, that is my job.
And also, to preach really hard, stupid stuff when a guy calls on the phone and says, here, come preach this.
So, let me ground you in a couple things.
Let me tell you a little bit about myself.
You're not going to hear a word I say if you don't trust me, know me, which will be really tough to do since I'm not even sitting next to you as I'm telling you these things.
But I will give it a try.
Because I'm going to say some things you're going to be like, yes.
And some things are like, no.
Like, we're going to be all over the map today.
Maybe we'll resonate 100%.
Maybe it'll be 2%.
I don't know.
But we'll find out.
But the first grounding is this.
If you follow after Jesus Christ, you and I are brothers and sisters.
Period.
End of sentence.
Hard stop.
Anything I say from here on out is about what it is for me to live out my faith and come alongside other men and women to figure out how to do that faithfully together.
So, sometimes we agree.
Sometimes we don't agree.
If we all agreed all the time, there would not be a Brethren Church denomination.
There would just be a church.
But through history, we have not agreed.
Right?
So, a little bit about me.
I was born in Texas.
Yep.
I wear cowboy boots on purpose.
I'm wearing them now.
Not because I wanted to preach it.
Because I wear cowboy boots on purpose all the time.
It grounds me.
It reminds me where I'm from.
I haven't lived in Texas since 1998.
It's been a minute.
I've actually lived in the city I live in now longer than I've ever lived anywhere else in my whole life.
And so, groundedness matters.
I'm going to cry.
Sorry.
Groundedness matters.
Where you're from.
What you know.
Who you are.
The people that speak into your life matters.
You are all from here.
Or maybe not.
I mean, it is really close to D.C.
I'm going to guess a lot of you guys are transplants.
Would that be fair?
Yeah?
So, that's where I was born.
I was born in Texas.
My dad was an oil field worker.
So, he moved us around a lot.
It felt like I was in the military.
We bounced a lot.
New Mexico.
Wherever the oil field took him, we went.
So, I've literally lived in the longest place in my whole life right now.
And that's nine years.
Nine years.
Where are your parents?
Who are your parents?
Who raised you?
Who are the people that spoke to you as you were being formed as a person?
Let's say what the Bible calls that.
Discipleship.
Who shaped you as a person?
Not just your parents, but also the community that you grew up in.
So, I grew up in a western part of the state of Texas.
The northwest in the panhandle.
If you've ever seen Texas, it looks like this.
I grew up here on the knuckle.
Okay?
Lubbock.
I was born in Lubbock.
I didn't go to Texas Tech.
I went to Texas A&M.
Joel loves that, by the way.
By the way, Doc, I think they call you Doc.
I heard him call you Doc.
Doc's a stupid Texas University fan.
I don't know why.
He has thought to think.
The best thing about it is I can shout really loud if I wanted to.
But here's the best part.
Doc, I think we like each other.
We've known each other for about half a minute now.
It's okay that he went to that school.
We'll move on.
But that shapes who you are, where you're from.
My dad was in the oil field.
We saw a lot of that.
New Mexico, back into Texas.
So it doesn't feel very southern where I grew up.
It feels very western where I grew up.
It's kind of hard.
You take Texas, divide it down the middle of the state through Dallas.
And the more east and south you go, the more southern it feels.
You get closer to Louisiana, the more south and western you feel.
It feels more like Mexico because you get closer to Mexico.
And the further you get up in north and west to the corner, the more western it feels.
And Arizona and Colorado and New Mexico kind of feels like that.
So it's a big place.
I did not really experience racism in my life until I moved to the state of Georgia.
Because everybody in my town was either brown or white.
They were from Mexico because the line moved on them in 1845.
Or they were white like me.
There were two African American students in my high school.
In four years that I was there.
Two.
Everybody was brown and white.
Wasn't a big deal.
Then I moved to Georgia and life changed for me.
Eyes were open.
It was shaped.
There was something different about black and white than brown and white.
Not that it's not racist everywhere in the world because there are.
But I wasn't shaped by that.
So our traditions, what do we practice?
The things that shape us, they shape who we are and what we do and how we talk and what we think about.
One of my favorite things about this job is I get to go around a lot of different places.
We all talk different.
I grew up saying y'all, right?
I talk to people about Virginia depending on what Virginian I talk to.
Sometimes they're southern.
Sometimes they're some weird like Atlantic thing, coast thing.
Right?
Because it's that weird mix of being in the south and not.
Go to Pennsylvania, they say yunes or some form of that weird word.
Right?
A lot of my examples are around food.
I went to one lady's house in Pennsylvania.
She served up something she called chili.
There were way too many ingredients for it to be chili.
It was more like soup.
But she called it chili.
That's fine.
It's not.
If it has anything but meat in it, it's not chili.
That's the argument I'll make.
She gives out some cornbread, which I was excited about.
And then she put maple syrup on the table.
Like, that's an abomination, people.
But she did it.
And she poured it on top.
And there was one guy with me who grew up in Northeast Ohio.
And he was super pumped.
And he slathered syrup.
And he was excited.
And I'm like, you're fired.
You're fired from this staff.
Who eats like that?
These things shape us.
They're cultural.
They're traditional.
They're rootedness.
There's stuff about these things.
And let me tell you, culture and rootedness, each strategy for breakfast every single day.
There's nothing you can come to with a strategy to think you're going to change a people.
If you don't address culture, if you don't address rootedness, you'll never change it.
Period.
But my culture, my heritage, where I'm from, where I grew up, is not the most important thing about me.
The most important thing about me is whose I am.
The fact that I follow Jesus Christ.
That's the most important thing.
That's the stuff that should shape me.
That's the culture that should shape who I am.
Over these other things.
But that's really a tough ask.
But the Lord can do it.
The Civil War will tell you that before the Civil War, you were a Virginian, a Texan, a Georgian, an Ohioan first.
Then you were an American after that.
But when Abraham Lincoln did, I know where I'm at, so bear with me.
When Abraham Lincoln changed things and started talking about union, yeah, come on now.
There's a man belching back there from Alabama.
I can hear him.
Started talking about union.
He began to change the conversation.
And so it's after Abraham Lincoln, not before, that we're American first and we're all just where are you from kind of story second.
That's after the Civil War.
Before the Civil War, most people didn't go 15 or 20 miles away from their home ever.
Ever, ever, ever.
And then the war started and it took men a long ways away from their homes.
You couldn't leave.
So this conversation, rooted before we go to the next thing, is this.
The best thing, the early church had difficult uphill battle because they were fighting against a culture that knew nothing about them and hated them, right?
But in that world, prior to the Civil War was even true.
So even in our time today, people didn't leave.
So when conversations got hard, you had two choices.
Don't talk to your neighbor ever again.
P.S. could be your brother.
Or you worked it out.
We don't live in that culture.
I've lived in five states, nine cities, like 22 houses in my lifetime.
If I don't like what I'm about to say, if you don't like what I'm about to say, you can go pack up and go down the street to another church.
The church doesn't have to really fight through this stuff anymore.
Because there's just another place to go.
And so we always are looking for some kind of homogeneity about who we are because we think that's going to help my church experience, help my place.
Because I feel safe because you think exactly like I do.
Prior to the modern era, that didn't exist.
You didn't leave.
So I ask you to listen.
Know that I love you.
And know that this matters.
Love each other.
Resist the urge with every fiber in your being to leave.
Resist it.
Because that's not what the kingdom has called us to.
It's not called us to that.
So, you might like some of this stuff.
You might not.
Now, your spiritual heritage.
Most of you have one.
If you've grown up in the church anywhere, shape, or form.
You guys live in the south.
It's pretty hard to probably never have run into it.
I used to always like to say when I was not in Georgia anymore, everybody in Georgia has been to church because their grandmama took them to church.
Right?
Now, they may not follow Jesus, but they know who he is.
It's a cultural understanding.
Who is Jesus?
I moved to California.
I meet a guy one time who had never, did not have a clue who Moses was.
Who Abraham was.
Who Adam was.
What the flood was.
And I'm like going, I don't have the mental capacity to.
I've never met somebody like that before.
So, there are places in the world where people are clean slates.
It's probably not here.
So, you have a tradition.
You were shaped by that tradition.
Every spiritual tradition has the things that they believe and they love and they care about those things.
The Brethren Church is one of those traditions.
If you did not know what that was before you walked in, there's two streams that feed the Brethren Church.
An Anabaptist stream.
I didn't say anti-Baptist.
Anna, A-N-A, Baptist.
It means re-baptizer in German.
It was a point of making fun of them.
The Germans who were Lutheran at the time thought that baptizing people as believers was actually not what the Scripture told them to do.
They actually persecuted the Anabaptists.
The re-baptizers.
They called them that on purpose.
It was kind of a derogatory term for them.
We are part of that stream.
If you grew up in a Baptist church, you baptized believers.
That's part of that.
That all came out of that stream of the radical reformation from the Anabaptist tradition.
You're also part of a pietist tradition.
Most churches are pietistic.
It just simply means that you believe your faith is personal.
It is something that you can wrestle with on your own inside of yourselves.
There's an inside, outward experience with Christ.
Pietistic.
There's a bunch of them.
Baptists, Methodists, Lutherans.
We, all of us.
Most traditions are pietistic.
So, we live at this confluence of believing that the Anabaptists, the tradition is that community matters.
What the community thinks about things matters.
This topic is really good for you to talk to each other about as a community.
Because what you believe matters.
I can't discern Scripture alone.
I need the help of my brothers and sisters to truly understand the Scriptures.
And then, this personal faith of the pietistic world that I am transformed from the inside out.
So, we're deeply relational people.
So, taking us to our heritage, we all kind of whole hog moved from Germany over to America into the Pennsylvania colony in the 1700s.
There was a man there by the name of Christopher Sauer who was a printer, a German printer.
And his rival was Ben Franklin.
Ben Franklin was printing in English.
And Christopher Sauer was printing in German.
But they did the same thing.
Almanacs, all the kinds of stuff.
But they were printing in different languages.
And Christopher Sauer, over his printing press, in his office, above the heart that's going into his thing,
it had a sign that said,
For the glory of God and for our neighbor's good.
So, this glory of God.
I am part of that tradition that says,
God matters to me personally.
But it also matters what happens in my community.
Personal, communal, coming together.
So, let me ground you here.
Philippians chapter 2.
If you would, turn over to your, in your Bibles if you would like.
We're going to be all over the place today.
I'll try.
I was told that I could go 50 minutes to an hour by your pastor.
He says, he says, he says he has a really hard time keeping it under an hour and a half.
And yet you like it.
He says a lot of things.
He sure does.
So, this is Paul speaking to the Philippians, the church and Philippi, talking about who Jesus is and kind of rooted them in the understanding of how they are supposed to be living out their faith.
Verse 1, chapter 2 of Philippians.
Therefore, if you have any encouragement from being united with Christ, if any comfort from his love, if any common sharing in the spirit, any tenderness and compassion, then make my joy complete.
By being like-minded, having the same love, being one in spirit, one in mind, do nothing out of selfish ambition or vain conceit.
Rather, in humility, value others above yourselves, not looking to your own interests, but each of you to the interests of others.
This is how believers are to walk through this world.
That's challenging.
Verse 5, in your relationships with one another, have the same mindset of Christ.
Now, we're going to ground you where Christ is, and he's telling us we should have the same mind, the same heart, the same spirit as Christ Jesus.
So, this power player, this person coming into a very political world with the Romans, people are begging him to take power, take control.
And this is what he does.
He, Christ, who being in the very nature God, did not consider equality with God something to be used to his own advantage.
Rather, he made himself nothing.
By taking on the very nature of a servant, being made in human likeness, and being found in appearance as a man, he humbled himself by becoming obedient to death, even death on a cross.
Therefore, God exalted him to the highest place, and gave him the name that is above every name.
That at the name of Jesus, every knee shall bow, in heaven and on earth and under the earth, and every tongue acknowledge that Jesus Christ is Lord to the glory of the God the Father.
This is God's kingdom.
This is the Jesus way.
This is the way, and when we say, before the Civil War, we would say we're Virginian or Texan first, we now say we are Christ first.
We're Christ kingdom first.
The kingdoms don't look like this.
It isn't God's kingdom, and then the American kingdom, or the Roman kingdom, or the, pick a kingdom, I don't care.
It isn't like this.
It is like this.
God's kingdom first.
We are called his children.
We are his citizens first.
And this is the mindset that we take.
We don't say we're American first and Jesus second.
We say it the other way around.
Now, that's a hard thing to say in a world that we believe a lot of times, not all the time, that we're striving to be God-like in our country.
Not always.
Maybe not recently.
But this is hard to hear when we say we're to be Christ first, American second, Roman second, Russian second, English second.
Pick one.
You're a brilliant man.
Thank you.
So, when Jesus taught us to pray, we can all say it together.
I'll try not to say it in the King James, but it probably will come out that way.
Our Father, who art in heaven, hallowed be thy name.
Thy kingdom come.
Stop.
Whose kingdom?
God's kingdom.
His kingdom come now.
Your will be done on earth as it is in heaven.
Every time we pray that prayer, we are praying down God's kingdom.
We are asking for God's kingdom to be more realized than it was before.
We are trying our best to live out what God has called us to do as his kingdom citizens.
And every time we pray that prayer, we're acknowledging.
It's like saying the pledge.
We're acknowledging his kingdom.
His will be done on earth as it is in heaven.
Sometimes they line up with our country's values.
Sometimes they don't.
But every time, our allegiance is there.
Now, I grew up in a good Baptist church that had all the pledges at Vacation Bible School, right?
We had to say the Pledge of Allegiance, the Pledge of Allegiance to the Christian flag, right?
Because that's important.
And the pledge to the Bible, right?
Remember, who did that as a kid?
Any of you guys do that as a kid?
Yeah, a few of you.
That was important.
Guess what order we set them in?
Oops.
It went American Christian Bible.
Every time.
Your kingdom come.
Your will be done.
We are citizens of a different kingdom.
Any country.
I don't care when.
I don't care what era.
I don't care what century it was in.
Any country's power, its king, its ruler.
Can lead its people to follow after Jesus.
It can do that.
It can do its best to do that.
But that country's power, that country's king, that country's authorities are not our king first.
Our king is Jesus.
And his kingdom is above every one of those kingdoms.
Every time.
Always.
We can do our best as men, because we have been called to do that.
And men and women, to lead our worlds in alignment with what God has called us to.
But the odds that we're going to get it right every time are nil, are zero, because we are fallen people.
There will come a time where you can start off right now, this little spot right here in Virginia.
You can claim it as a sovereign nation.
Start waving a flag and sticking a thing in the ground.
At some point in its history, some man or woman is going to kind of pervert something.
There's something they think they're going to do, and it's going to be okay, and it's going to be right.
And then it's going to turn into something, and it's going to be out of alignment with what God calls us to do.
Because we are infallible.
We are not infallible people.
We're fallible.
Power is a thing.
And it's hard to lead with.
It's hard to lead through.
So Philippians 2, 10 and 11, again, it says,
Then at the name of Jesus, every knee, not some knees, not just bad people's knees, not just evil people's knees,
every single knee on the planet shall bow in heaven and earth and under the earth.
Man, that's all the knees, right?
I don't know what's under the earth here.
We could probably get into a word study on what Paul was meaning by that.
And every tongue will confess and acknowledge that Jesus Christ is Lord.
That's coming.
Turn to the end of the book.
It tells you.
It's coming.
So Jesus comes, and he proclaimed to the kingdom of the world, Roman at this point in history,
that he is God.
He is king.
Christ's resurrection as God's victory.
The Roman cross was used to dominate people.
And he used it to dominate death.
Christ's resurrection as God's victory was what dominated the political powers of the day.
Even everything you could throw at me, Rome, everything.
You only had one move, and that was to kill me.
Right?
You could do a lot of other stuff.
They beat him.
They could do a lot of stuff, but they killed him, and that still didn't work.
As believers in that kingdom, our engagement, our engagement can challenge the motivations of modern political systems.
We can challenge them when they need to be challenged.
We can serve in them when they need to have people serve in them.
We can challenge them, too.
All politics.
Tim Keller was a pastor.
He's passed away now in New York.
He says, all politics are provisional.
Our hope is the eternal kingdom of God.
Earthly politics are temporary.
God's eternal kingdom is permanent.
So how we engage in that matters.
How we deal with that matters.
Some people grow up in traditions where America and Bible are kind of linked in.
If you grew up in the South, this feels really like that.
Right?
It's hard to separate.
But that doesn't mean you have to live like that.
Right?
So I grew up in the South.
Grew up in Texas.
I mean, it's the buckle of the Bible belt for crying out loud.
Right?
And I grew up in a Baptist place, and I moved to Georgia.
It might be the weird back part of the buckle belt of the Bible belt.
I don't know.
And so I didn't run into us, the Brethren Church, through a guy who was a friend and a pastor and a mentor.
And I start digging into this idea of Anabaptism and its political witness.
Now, if you don't know a lot about that, let me give you a sense of what that could look like.
Anybody heard of the Amish?
Yeah?
Amish or Anabaptists.
Their political witness is complete separation.
Get completely out of the world.
Don't engage in it whatsoever.
Stay as far away as you can.
They speak another language, right?
They speak Pennsylvania Dutch.
They call us English.
That's what they call it.
If you run into an Amish person, they would describe you as an English person.
They are separate.
That is a way to navigate through an Anabaptist tradition where it says that engaging in this political witness in politics really is something they're not called to at all.
So I run into this, and I begin to process this, and I feel like, okay, I don't want to stop driving cars.
I like electricity.
Like, okay, so what part of this can I pick up?
So our tradition, the Brethren Church, if you were to see us prior to 1885, there would be no difference.
You could not tell if you were not, like, sitting down talking to them.
Because guess what we had?
Really long beards.
No mustaches.
The ladies covered their heads.
You know, all the things you would see in an Amish community, we carried.
Now, we modernized after the 1880s, but Amish didn't.
But our theology is very similar in this idea.
So we were pacifists until World War II.
So a lot of our churches then struggled with this political witness of, oh, my gosh, all these men are going off to war, and none of our men are going off to war.
But prior to World War II, if you were to go to war, you would not be a part of the church any longer.
This idea that we don't take up arms, we do not kill another person, because every person's life matters, regardless of what they believe.
So we held that, right?
And so I'm navigating these traditions and trying to understand that, and there's a point to this story.
So I consider myself kind of a conscientious objector.
I'll use the word pacifist.
Pacifist.
I don't want to take up arms against anyone.
I went to military school.
Like, almost every one of my aunts and uncles, all of them were in the military.
This is a tradition that I have been a part of my whole life.
And I've literally taken, I've got two antique guns in my house.
They've got trigger locks on them, and they're in the attic, so my children can't find them.
Like, this is a posture that I've taken, this political witness of understanding what it means to follow after Jesus, because I don't want to bear arms against anyone.
And I don't mean, like, sons out, guns out, bear arms, right?
I'm talking about guns.
I live in Ohio now.
We're kind of this weird, purple-y state.
I'm glad somebody thought that was funny.
Thank you.
We're this purple-y state, right?
We're sometimes red, sometimes blue.
So we get a lot of people canvassing our neighborhood.
And this guy, like, last political cycle, knocked on my door.
Hey, I got a lot of pamphlets here.
He just, it's automatically assumed that I'm a dude, and I drive a truck, so I must be conservative.
I don't know.
I don't know what they think, right?
So this guy just starts handing me stuff.
He's like, here's Second Amendment, and da-da-da-da-da-da.
And I was like, okay, I really appreciate that, man, but I'm a pacifist.
And that guy was like, what?
And, like, his whole face went, phew.
Like, he had no script for that.
Like, he had no, like, what am I supposed to say to that?
He just, like, went blank.
Because, you know, he has a script.
He's been taught to teach this stuff out, right?
And so he's like, I got a pamphlet on the judges.
Do you want that?
I was like, no, really, thank you.
Okay.
And so he, like, walked away dumbfounded.
Because this tradition that I'm a part of has influenced me.
And so we can say a lot of different things about where we're from and what we do and how we believe about stuff.
And it would lead us to different conclusions.
About what it means to live these things out.
But they're all provisional.
Some of you may choose not to vote.
Some of you may choose to get involved at the homeless shelter in town.
Not just because homeless people need help.
But it's an active witness to the world around you.
There's different ways you can take those things on.
And I don't think anybody is wrong in doing those things.
It's like, what does the Scripture say?
And how do I live those things out faithfully in my life?
So remember that earthly politics are temporary.
And God's kingdom is eternal.
So all of our life is interpreted through this understanding.
The Philippians 2 passage about who Jesus is.
There's a reason that Paul writes these things.
It's important.
And then Peter picks up on the motif a little bit too.
So if you want to flip over to 1 Peter chapter 2.
Peter starts calling us exiles.
Foreigners.
Picking up on this language of being a part of a different kingdom.
You're God's kingdom first.
Whatever else second.
And because you're in this kingdom.
And you live in all these other kingdoms.
You are actually in exile.
Maybe a foreigner from somewhere else.
If you're a transplant to Virginia.
Or you've been a transplant to another state.
You know for a fact that's hard.
Exegeting culture.
Understanding weird things like putting syrup on cornbread.
Like you got to figure that stuff out when you move.
Or you feel kind of like you stick out.
But Peter's reminding us in 1 Peter that that's okay.
The Jesus way is not the way of the world.
The way of the cultures around us.
That Jesus culture comes first.
So in chapter 2.
I think it's verse 11.
Dear friends.
I urge you as foreigners and exiles.
To abstain from sinful desires which wage war against your soul.
Live such good lives among the pagans.
That though they accuse you of doing wrong.
They may see your good deeds.
And glorify God on the day he visits.
You are different.
There's something different about you.
Pastor Ryan came up and said.
Hey if you're new here.
And somebody invited you.
And you're like.
Man there's something different about them.
I want to go check that out.
That's what he's talking about.
There's something just askew.
Like we think sometimes a world like this.
But it's like watching a 3D movie without the glasses on.
Right?
It's like that.
There's something just slightly different.
Some kingdoms are like over here.
And God's kingdom is over here.
Some kingdoms don't look nothing like God's kingdom.
Some kingdoms are really close.
Sometimes they line up just real nice and perfect.
And we think we got it made.
But then all of a sudden something happens.
And they go.
And they're just askew again.
And we can't.
We scramble to find our glasses.
To put them back on.
So we can see what that thing is.
That's bulging out of us at the movie theater.
Going on in chapter 4 of 1 Peter.
Peter says this.
Verse 7.
To the end of all things.
The end of all things is near.
Therefore be alert and of sober mind.
That you may pray.
Above all love each other deeply.
Which is how we are relating to each other here.
Because love covers over a multitude of sins.
Offer hospitality to one another without grumbling.
Each of you should use whatever gift you have received to serve others.
As faithful stewards of God's grace in these various forms.
So he's picking up on this exile motif.
There's something different about you.
There's something that can be seen about you that's different.
He picked up on this motif.
He just didn't make this up.
This actually comes from the Old Testament.
In Jeremiah.
In Israel is captured by Babylon.
And they're drug into exile.
Jeremiah is a prophet who is speaking to the people of Israel during that time.
If you want to turn over to Jeremiah 29 you can.
Now who's got Jeremiah 29 11 on some piece of wood or something stuck to somewhere in your house.
Right.
Like this is a thing.
This is a pretty common thing.
Jeremiah 29 11.
I have plans for you.
Right.
That's on the next page here.
Here we go.
For I know the plans I have made for you declares the Lord.
Plans to prosper you.
To not harm you.
Plans to give you hope and a future.
Amazing.
Thank God that he has a plan for us.
God says that to Israel on their way in to exile.
Not on the way out.
On the way in.
Seventy years.
Seventy years of exile.
Out of their home country.
Ripped out.
Picked up.
Taken to another place.
And so Jeremiah says to them.
God has a hope for you.
God has a plan for you.
There is something coming that is good.
God is not surprised by this.
God is not surprised by the fact that you live in America in Virginia in 2024.
Not a shocker.
He knew.
He knew what was going to take place in our world today.
Not surprised.
He knew who was going to be our potential elected officials after November the 3rd or 4th.
Right.
Not surprised.
Be kind of weird for God to go.
Oh snap.
Caesar Augustus made it.
Dang it.
Now what am I going to do?
Did not think that through.
Not true.
Clearly I left off the modern political names on purpose.
But let's read Jeremiah 29.
Starting in verse 4.
The first 4 or 5 verses here just tell you that there is a letter just being written.
Jeremiah is telling you all about it.
And then there is this letter starting in verse 4.
This is what the Lord Almighty, the God of Israel says to all those carried into exile.
This is to you.
You are in exile.
You are a foreigner in another kingdom.
If you follow after Jesus Christ, this letter is to you.
Build houses and settle down.
Plant gardens and eat what they produce.
Marry and have sons and daughters.
Find wives for your sons and give your daughters into marriage so they too may have sons and daughters.
Increase in number.
Do not decrease.
Also, seek.
Okay.
This is the...
Sorry.
It's one thing to say, hey, just have a good time.
Make sure you stay together in your families.
Make sure your kids find husbands and wives.
Have a bunch of grandbabies.
That sounds amazing.
I'm not a grandparent, but I'm so looking forward to it.
I'm really excited about it.
That sounds fine.
I can handle that.
But verse 7.
Also, seek the peace and prosperity of the city to which I have carried you into exile.
You want me to care about the people that hurt me on purpose?
The Babylonians don't care about me.
The Babylonians want to see me crushed.
Why did they pick me up and take me out of Jerusalem anyway?
Because they want to crush our kingdom.
And that's the way they did it.
They would scoop up all the best and they'd take all the best leaders, all the young men and women,
all the people that have capacity, they would whisk them off into exile.
So have kids, have babies, have grandbabies, and then seek the peace and prosperity of the city to which I have carried you into exile.
Pray to the Lord for it.
Pray for this place that wants to exile you and hurt you.
Because if it prospers, you too will prosper.
And then he says,
For I know the plans I have for you, declares the Lord.
Plans to prosper you and not to harm you.
Plans to give you a hope and a future.
So if we're a part of God's kingdom, we are a citizen there first.
We are called to care about every other kingdom that comes in contact with us.
Even if we disagree with it, that's painful.
You're called to care about the flourishing of your city, your country, your world.
You should care about it.
We do it differently.
We do it by humbling ourselves, caring for one another,
not abandoning each other in our time of need,
not walking away when it's hard.
There's something different about being a citizen of the kingdom
than being a citizen of any other kingdom that's ever existed in the history of the world.
We sacrifice.
We give away.
We have prosperity, so therefore we give it away.
We care about the people that are hurting.
We care about the orphan, the widow.
We are called to care about this place
because I don't, have you done anything on Revelation yet?
Is that coming anytime soon?
Oh, good.
He's really excited that I brought that up.
So at the end, when you read the end of the book,
it isn't an I'll fly away book.
You're Southern enough to know what that means, right?
Like it's not an I'll fly away end of the book.
Heaven and earth come together
and we live here with the Lord.
So we should care about the place that he has planted us.
We should care about his thriving.
We should care about his flourishing.
And sometimes that means that some people really care about the earth
and we care about trees and we care about the grass.
And some of us who grew up somewhere else go,
ew, that feels like a tree hugger to me.
Right?
That doesn't feel like Jesus.
That feels very, very liberal.
But you can care about the earth
and care about people and still be in God's kingdom.
Right?
I'm sorry.
If there's a tree hugger in the room, I apologize.
Don't let the world shroud this calling.
It's so easy to do.
It is so easy to do.
And we can blame Constantine for this.
Right?
Constantine in 300 AD decided that Christianity
was going to be the way of his kingdom.
And a kingdom, the kingdoms became linked.
And pretty much since then,
most Western societies have been linked with Christianity
in some way, shape, or form.
And that's okay.
There's nothing wrong with that.
But when we allow the kingdom of the world
to shroud over the kingdom of heaven,
we've made a mistake.
World kingdom values do not trump
over the top of the kingdom values of Christ.
So every time we pray the Lord's Prayer,
we are reminded to be citizens of God's kingdom.
Every knee will bow.
Every nation, tribe, people, empire, king, queen
will bow their knee at the foot of Jesus.
That was true of the Romans, the Persians, the Greeks,
the Ottoman Empire, the English Empire,
the Japanese Empire.
It's true for every democracy everywhere in the world.
They will kneel before King Jesus.
Sometimes the world gets really close
and it begins to look like we're there.
But then when it kind of gets blurry,
it becomes weird.
I was at a conference
and the McKays were there with me
and there was this guy,
he's a really smart guy
because most of those people were.
And he talked about how that Christians
should be an unreliable political partner.
Because we're kingdom first,
world second.
So if the kingdom values line up with this thing,
this idea,
this ideology,
I'm gonna be about that.
I don't care what side of the aisle it's on.
So that makes you an unreliable political partner, right?
If you want me always to be blue,
well, then sometimes I'm red.
Well, if you always want me to be red,
well, sometimes I'm because
this is where the kingdom lines up
and I don't care what blue and red spectrum it falls on.
I'm always about the kingdom first.
Which makes us unreliable.
Now, I will say in America,
that's not been true.
Probably since the 80s.
Now, they talk about us Christians,
us evangelicals
in a very broad brush stroke swath of people.
And somehow we all seem to go vote exactly the same.
We know that's not true.
But we should be about the kingdom,
which then makes us unreliable.
Because I'm about the kingdom first
and the flourishing of the city
but I'm going to do it with Jesus' values,
not the world's values.
So, final thing here in Galatians for you.
Chapter 6.
So, Jeremiah reminds us,
he writes us a letter,
tells us to be about the flourishing
of the place that God has planted us.
And Paul reminds us of the same thing
and he helps us
as we're living out this spirit.
If we read Galatians 5,
the fruit of the Spirit,
he's talking about this idea
of what happens when we walk in the spirit
and we do that together in the spirit.
Love and peace and patience
and kindness and goodness
and gentleness and faithfulness
and self-control.
And then in chapter 6,
chapter 6, verse 8.
It says,
whoever sows to please their flesh
from the flesh
will reap destruction.
Whoever sows to please the spirit
from the spirit
will reap eternal life.
And verse 9,
so let us not become weary
in doing good.
For at the proper time,
we will reap a harvest
if we do not give up.
Therefore,
as we have opportunity,
let us do good
to all people,
especially to those
who belong
to the family of believers.
Regardless of what somebody believes,
regardless of where they were born,
what side of the aisle
they are on,
I'm called to care
about them too.
Not just the people
that like me,
who I like,
who I think like me,
and dress like me.
Like, not just those people,
because I like them.
That's easy.
I'm going to do that anyway.
But also,
good for my community,
for the flourishing,
for the common good
of the people around me,
all people.
So as exiles and foreigners
from another kingdom,
grow where you are planted.
For the glory of God
and for your neighbor's good.
Wherever a body of believers
is planted,
we are to make
a transformational difference
in that community.
a guy named N.T. Wright
and Michael Byrd,
they wrote a book
called Jesus and the Powers.
It's a really good book.
It talks a lot about politics
and the church.
And they talked about
where do I get involved?
How do I engage now
with this reality in mind?
That I'm kingdom first,
God's kingdom first,
all other kingdoms second.
It's getting into your community.
It's not that you don't
run for office.
I would not.
That is not a conviction
that I have.
But in this season,
as far as I am able,
I'm gonna go find
a ministry to partner with.
I'm gonna,
maybe it's here in Canvas.
Maybe it's here in the city.
Find a friend I can pray with.
Join a group of people
who might pray for peace
for Israel and Palestine.
Boy, that's a thing, right?
Contact my member of Congress.
Tell them where I think
they're wrong.
I'm sure they would love
to hear it.
Get in with these people.
These people here,
they're your brothers and sisters,
and dig in to understand
the needs of this community.
Because all politics is local.
The world has convinced us
that all politics is national.
And if we could just fix that,
everything else would be fixed.
We know that's not true.
All politics is local.
So understand the needs
of this community.
Advocate for those needs.
Run for the school board.
I got a friend
that ran for the school board.
He wished he'd never done it.
It was so hard
because it was during COVID.
Put your fears aside
and let your faith in Jesus
fill your heart
for the stranger,
for the widow,
for your neighbor.
So Wright and Byrd say this.
Perhaps the single greatest threat
that is not the rise of secularism,
it's not the emptying of our churches,
even though we're dealing with that,
but it's the apathy
and the indifference of the churches
that are still here.
The people are too self-absorbed,
too affluent
to care about anything
outside of their own
social media bubble.
So behind their own
circle of friends,
they don't get beyond
their own circle of friends
and beyond their view
of their front lawns.
And too many so-called disciples
are committed to Jesus
to the point of convenience,
not to the point
where their discipleship
costs them something.
Yet Jesus bids us
to come and follow him.
He actually comes
and bids us to die
to ourselves, right?
And to live,
to leave behind
all the worldly trinkets
and to do hard things
on purpose,
crazy things,
impossible things
for no other good reason
than our king told us to.
Our king, Jesus,
walks alongside us.
He's suffering with us
on this earth
and he endeavors
to embody us
with his spirit
to do that work.
Was there a song
at the end?
Should I call the band
back up?
Yeah?
No?
They're gonna come then.
So I'm gonna remind you
to live a life
worthy of the calling
that you have received.
I promise you
if you would love to
and I can't
because I gotta drive
home to Ohio,
we could talk
for about 10 hours
about any one
of these things
in very deep depths.
Find somebody
you don't agree with
on a topic
and just sit there
and first,
before you start
any conversation,
commit to not leaving.
commit to that person
because they're your brother
or your sister
and the Lord
that you agree
that you are kingdom people first
and all politics second.
So may the Lord bless you.
May you know
and experience
the fruit of the Spirit
as exiles
and foreigners
in a place
that is not your home.
May that place thrive.
May you be the reason
this place thrives
and may you not grow weary
in doing good
for the day of the Lord
is near.
Amen.
We're gonna end
with a song
and taking the bread and cup
and so if you didn't get
a chance to grab one
on the way in,
I invite you
to grab one.
We practice open communion
which means
if you're in here
and you would say
that you're a follower
of Jesus,
you're welcome,
more than welcome
to partake
in the bread and the cup.
As Stephen was talking,
I was thinking about communion
and how these two things
connect
because
the beautiful thing
about being a pastor
for as long as I have
is I've never found
a Sunday
where communion
didn't connect
with whatever
was being said
because communion
is at the heart
of the gospel
and the gospel
is at the heart
of whatever
we should be saying
from the front
of the stage.
But as he was talking
about these things
like these kingdoms
lining up
and becoming askew,
I was thinking about
power.
That's,
in my opinion,
where most things
come askew
because most kingdoms
believe that the way
in which they lead,
the way in which
they have victory,
they accomplish
their goals,
their corporate tasks
is that they have
to be stronger,
smarter,
better than
the kingdoms around.
And the Lord's Supper
is Jesus'
weekly reminder,
regular reminder
that he actually
accomplished victory
through death,
through sacrificially
laying down his life.
And that's how
the kingdom of God
will be visible
on earth
as it is in heaven
if we as followers
of Jesus
are willing
to lay down
our preferences.
We're willing
to follow the example.
This is why he says
as often as you do this,
do this in remembrance
of me
until I come.
I won the victory.
I'm coming back.
Victory will be visible
for all of eternity.
But until that day comes,
it is your opportunity
to follow my example,
to lay down your life
for the good
of your neighbor.
So,
if you're in here,
you're a follower of Jesus,
I invite you
to take this wafer
as a representation
as a reminder
that your Savior
became worthy
not through riding
on a horse
into Rome
and taking over power,
but through riding
on a donkey
and laying down
his life
for you
to take this
and remember
our Savior.
Let's drink.
Drink the juice
as a representation
of Christ's blood
to get for you.
Stephen mentioned Revelation.
We haven't talked
about it that much
from stage
because I have
some work to do
on my own
which I have
been doing
and right now
I'm in Revelation
4 and 5.
Most theologians
call Revelation
4 and 5
heaven as it is now.
all the elders,
all the saints
bow
in constant
continuous worship
of the Lord.
That is happening
as we speak
and yet here on earth
we feel the tension
of Jesus' victory
not fully being here yet.
It's like we see it
but we don't see it.
Heaven sees it clearly.
So you're invited
right now
as we get ready
to conclude service
to join with what
heaven has been doing
throughout the service
and will continue
to do for all of creation
until Christ returns.
And that is to declare
Jesus Christ
worthy of it all.
Please stand
and we'll finish
with the song.
and all the elders
pass their crowns
before the Lamb
of God
and sing,
sing it again
and we sing
all the saints
and angels
And all the elders
and all the elders
pass their crowns
before the Lamb
of God
and sing
You are worthy
of it all
For from you
are all things
and to you
You deserve the glory
Oh, and all the saints
And all the saints
and angels
bow their crowns
And all the elders
and all the elders
cast their crowns
before the Lamb
of God
and sing
You are worthy
of it all
you are worthy